<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Plain truth vvithout feare or flattery: or a true discovery of the unlawfulnes of the Presbyterian government, it being inconsistent with monarchy, and the peoples liberties; and contrary both to the Protestation and Covenant. The end of establishing the militia of London in such hands as it is now put into by the new ordinance. The betraying votes, and destructive practises, of a trayterous party in the House of Commons, concerning certain pettions [sic] for liberty and justice. Also a vindication of his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax concerning certain scurrulous words uttered by some of the said faction. VVith the meanes and wayes that must be used to obtain reliefe against the said tyrannous usurpers; and for reducing the Parliament to its due rights, power and priviledges, in the preservation of the kingdomes lawes and liberties / VVritten by Amon VVilbee.</title>
            <author>Wilbee, Amon.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2112</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E516_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204095</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863796</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863796</idno>
            <idno type="VID">164386</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96470)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 164386)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 81:E516[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Plain truth vvithout feare or flattery: or a true discovery of the unlawfulnes of the Presbyterian government, it being inconsistent with monarchy, and the peoples liberties; and contrary both to the Protestation and Covenant. The end of establishing the militia of London in such hands as it is now put into by the new ordinance. The betraying votes, and destructive practises, of a trayterous party in the House of Commons, concerning certain pettions [sic] for liberty and justice. Also a vindication of his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax concerning certain scurrulous words uttered by some of the said faction. VVith the meanes and wayes that must be used to obtain reliefe against the said tyrannous usurpers; and for reducing the Parliament to its due rights, power and priviledges, in the preservation of the kingdomes lawes and liberties / VVritten by Amon VVilbee.</title>
                  <author>Wilbee, Amon.</author>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8, [16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and published for the information, advice, and benefit, of the poor, oppressed, betrayed, and almost destroyed commons of England,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editions/issues of this work appear with differing author statements: Written by I.L. (i.e. John Lilburne), or, Written by Amon Wilbee. NUC attributes the work to John Lilburne, Wing (CD-ROM, 1996) attributes to Amon WIlbee. The Lilburne entries for this title have be cancelled in Wing.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 2d London".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  History, (17th century) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:164386:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> PLAIN TRVTH VVithout FEARE or FLATTERY: Or a true DISCOVERY OF The unlawfulnes of the Presbyterian government, it being inconſiſtent with Monarchy, and the Peoples Liberties; and contrary both to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation and Covenant. The end of eſtabliſhing the Militia of London in ſuch hands as it is now put into by the new Ordinance. The betraying Votes, and deſtructive practiſes, of a trayterous Party in the Houſe of Commons, concerning certain Pettions for Liberty and Juſtice. ALSO A Vindication of his Excellency Sir THOMAS FAIRFAX concerning certain ſcurrulous words uttered by ſome of the ſaid Faction. VVITH The meanes and ways that muſt be uſed to obtain reliefe againſt the ſaid ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannous Uſurpers; and for reducing the Parliament to its due Rights, Power and Priviledges, in the preſervation of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes Lawes and Liberties VVritten by AMON VVILBEE</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſaiah 3 12, 13, 14.</bibl>
               <p>Children are extortioners of my People, and women have rule over them: O my People; they that lead thee, cauſe thee to erre, and deſtroy the way of thy paths.</p>
               <p>The Lord ſhall enter into judgement with the Ancients of his People, and the Princes thereof: for yee have eaten up the Vinyard, the ſpoyle of the poore is in your houſes.</p>
               <p>What have yee to do that yee beat my People to pieces, and grinde the faces of the poore ſaith the Lord, even the Lord of Hoſts?</p>
               <p>Woe be to the wicked, it ſhall be evill with him, for the reward of his hands ſhall be given him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed and publiſhed for the information, advice, and benefit, of the poore oppreſſed, betrayed, and almoſt deſtroyed Commons of England. 1647.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:164386:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:164386:2"/>
            <head>PLAIN TRVTH VVithout Feare, or Flattery.</head>
            <p>IN the 28. Pſalm, Verſe 6. the Spirit of God ſpeaking there of Judges and Rulers, ſaith they are Gods, and all of them children of the moſt high; but he telleth them they ſhall dye like men, and fall as one of the Princes. We unhappy men of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land have at this time a generation of ambitious imperious men, ſome of both Houſes of Parliament, whoſe names ye may elſewhere find; who by their power and ſubtill practiſes, do frame and aſsume to themſelves a ſupreame power over us, and would faine be taken for Gods, and ſonnes of the moſt high by us; yet they neither rule us like Gods, nor demeane themſelves amongſt us as children of the moſt high: but rule us like Tyrants (a degenerate kind which God never made nor owned) and demean themſelves more like children of diſobedience (ſerving their own baſe luſts and pleaſures) then children of the moſt high: for were they ſuch, they would ſeeke the will of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heaven, and good of his People. But the Spirit ſaith they ſhall dye like men; the which it may be doubted theſe men believe not; but rather with the Athieſticall Epicure thinke they ſhall dye like Beaſts, and that the ſoule, aſwell as the body returnes to the (pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam materiam,) and ſo, if they can but eſcape the ſtroake of juſtice here, they dreame not of hearing of their wicked deeds hereafter: and therefore they have reſolved (it appeares) for the accompliſhment of their own unrighteous ends, (after the manner of all Athieſticall Stateſmen, who caſt the feare of God, and conſideration of death and judgement behind them) to aſsay all wayes and meanes of wickednes, as to vow and not pay, to promiſe and not performe, ſweare and forſweare, covenant and breake, to feign, flatter, and play the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, (I had almoſt ſaid the devill) to betray, deſtroy, rob, ſpoyle, oppreſs, and violate all law and rule of government, infringe all rights, and liberties, impriſon, perſecute, deceive their truſt, requite evill for good, and do all manner of miſchiefe and injuſtice, even what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Sathan, and their wicked hearts ſhall prompt them unto; inſomuch that whatſoever they ſay or make ſhew of, their evil doings declare that they believe not an immortallity and judgement: they profeſs themſelves Chriſtians, but if yee obſerve and conſider their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, you muſt ſay (and if you were a ſtranger you would ſware) they were heathens; yea they do worſe then heathens; for did ever heathens take the name of their inſenſible Gods of wood and ſtone, ſo frequently and ſolemnly into their mouthes, by way of oath and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, as theſe men have done, and had it ſo little in reverence, and ſo little reſpect to what they have ſworne; as theſe men have had the name of the great and terrible God of heaven, and of their oathes made unto him? read all Stories, and ſearch all Centuries of Ages, and if there be any ſuch example of perjury, and ſwearing falſly by their God, equivalent to the example of theſe men, of this generation, I will freely offer my ſelfe for a ſacrafice, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piare my offence againſt their holines: and yet they are ready with Agurs Harlot Pro. 30. 20. to wipe their mouthes, and ſay we have done no wickednes. But that the truth may be made apparent, and expatiated, let us heare their promiſes, vowes and ſpeeches, and compare their deeds and practiſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt they do in the Proteſtation, promiſe, vow, and proteſt, in the preſence of Almighty God (whom ſure they thinke is like the God of Baals Prieſts, that could neither heare nor ſee) to maintain and defend with their lives, powers, and eſtates, the true reformed Proteſtant Religion, expreſsed in the doctrine of the Church of England, againſt all Popery, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh innovations within this Realme, contrary to the ſame doctrine, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Yet they are now ſetting up, and have ſet up ſo farre as in them lyeth, a Religion never before heard of within this Realme, and quite contrary to the profeſsed doctrine of the Church of England, it being wholly oppoſite unto Chriſt, and a meere Popiſh innovation, brought out of Scotland, and violently impoſed upon us: And thus it comes to paſs, by the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:164386:3"/> confederacy of a haughty trayterous Party in the Houſes of Parliament, of which are the Earles of Mancheſter and Stamford, Sir Phillip Stapleton, M. Hollis, and others, with the proud covetous Prieſts, for the advancement of their deſigne of uſurpation and lordlines both over his Majeſty and us, vow and proteſt in like manner, to maintain and defend the Kings royall perſon, honour and eſtate, and the lawfull rights and liberties of the Subject, and every one that ſhould make the ſaid Proteſtation, in purſuance of the ſame; and that they will not for hope, feare, or other reſpect, relinquiſh this promiſe, vow, and proteſtation. And do they not accordingly maintain and defend the Kings royall perſon, honour, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate? His perſon with a company of Commiſſioners of their own ſtamp and temper, and with a guard of able Horſmen and Souldiers, (debauched Graves his Regiment) as if they were affraid to intruſt any of the honeſt Commanders about him) as if he were rather a Prince of Theeves, then a Prince of three Kingdomes, or of a free People? and his honour and eſtate they defend with all the power and might they can; taking the Supream power upon themſelves to grant Pardons, ſell the Lands purchaſed with the lives and money of the People, without the Peoples conſent; make Judges, create Lord Keepers or Chancellours, (and yet the King in preſence, for they cannot now pretend a neceſſity by his abſence) and making uſe of his name to violate all Law; oppreſs the People; and to commit all injuſtice: in a word, to deſtroy our liberties, and to execute their own Arbitrary wills. They ſpeake of having the Kings power with them virtually; but wee can neither ſee nor find any of its proper vertue either among them, or from them; for his Majeſties Regall power is juſt and mercifull, regulated by Law, preſervative and corrective; and not unjuſt, cruell, irregular, and illegall, defacing and deſtructive; as the effects have been of the power which the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament hath exerciſed. And concerning the Kings eſtate and revennues; no queſtion but it is accumulated, and that they have it in banke, for they have been very parcimonious Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards; they can hardly ſpare either the maſter money for his neceſſities, or his Servants any for wages: He, like a Ward, or Pupill, is at their ſet allowance, and content with the pittance his late Tutors and Guardians will allow him; I doubt not but it will prove that ſome of them have made better allowance to themſelves both our of his eſtate, and the Republiques alſo.</p>
            <p>Second, how by reaſon of the predominancy and power of this tyrannous Party in both Houſes, whoſe malignant pernicious influence hath been, and ſtill is diffuſive throughout all the Parliaments actions; all thoſe which have taken this Vow and Proteſtation, are and have been defended in purſuance of the ſame, it is ſufficiently manifeſt: For who but they that endeavour to maintain the true reformed Proteſtant Religion, according to the doctrine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsed in the Church of England, in the power and purity of it, are hated, illegally proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and perſecuted, vilifyed, and reviled, and he is moſt favoured, and ſooneſt preferred, that can ſhew himſelfe moſt virulent, and violent againſt them? And if you do but ſken, or looke (like a Hare) on the one ſide, at the Kings Crown and dignity; you preſently incurre through the powerfull Votes of this Party, the Parliaments high diſlike and diſpleaſure, and it is a ſufficient badge, that you are an enemy, (becauſe you are ſo to Traytors to the State; witnes the high diſlike of the Armies wiſe, and juſt demand, of his Majeſties royall aſsent to an Act of indempnity: and truly if they take a bare Parliament Ordinance without the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all aſsent, I will not give them one farthing for their ſecurity; and it will be found that their Judges, Chancellours, Exciſe men, and Sequeſtrators, are in the ſame caſe as the Souldiers: And to endeavour or petition for liberty, according to the Proteſtation, is as much as to beg a Priſon, to ſue for juſtice, is to be accounted ſeditious; in a word, to be ſincere and honeſt, is to be adjudged worthy of no truſt, imployment, or preſerment.</p>
            <p>But to make the truth, and the wicked practiſes and purpoſes of this deſtroying Party in both Houſes, yet more plain and open; theſe cunning contrivers, of our intended Vaſsalage and thraldome, frame a combination and confederacy by covenant with the Scots, and by power and ſubtilty ſurprize and inſnare therein the whole Parliament and Kingdome: (the which I pray read, and obſerve;) In their feigned profeſſion of ſorrow they acknowledge, that their not prizing the Goſpell, nor labouring to receive Chriſt into their hearts, (and they ſay truly) hath been the cauſe of all other fames amongſt us: And therefore with their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:164386:3"/> hands lifted up to the moſt high God, they do ſolemnly ſware ſincerely to endeavour a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion in the three Kingdomes, in doctrine, worſhip, diſcipline, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according to the word of God, and the example of the beſt reformed Churches: now what meanes this juggle, and to the example of the beſt reformed churches? above they ſweare to endeavour a reformation, and what ſincerity is here, to make mens impure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, equivalent to the infallible rule of Gods word? to make (dogma preſbyteri) the opinion of the Prieſt, adaquate to the unalterable laſt Will and Teſtament of Jeſus Chriſt? only here by this Foyſt, theſe deceitfull Spirits endeavour to bring in ſomething of their own, that with their claw-back Prieſts, they may ſeem to have ſomething to do with Chriſt in his Church government, and to ſit cheeke by joule with him in his throne: and thus they do ſtill diſ-eſteem the ineſtimable benefit of the Goſpell, and oppoſe it in the power and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it; even as their Fathers did, ſo do they, harden their hearts againſt the Lord. If the word of God be a ſufficient rule to reform and govern the Church by; what need then of any other pattern or platforme? The beſt reformed Churches which are this day in Europe need reformation, yea the pure Church of Scotland, notwithſtanding all their pretences.</p>
            <p>For if you obſerve our bretherens various double dealings, turnings and windings, ſelf-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and advantage-making in every buſines they tranſact, or negotiate with us, farre unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming men pretending ſo great conſcientiouſnes in all things, and ſo highly profeſſing the power of Religion, in purenes of life and converſation. At firſt they were againſt the King; then while he was with them, they ſpeake and write highly for him, and now they have made the moſt they can of him, they are again become adverſaries to him; one while they preſs one part of their deceitfull Covenant; as at firſt <note place="margin">The Scors have made more of the King, then Judas did of the King of heaven.</note> they did that part, for bringing evill inſtruments unto condigne pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, whilſt that Delinquents troubled them: Afterwards, when by craft they had gotten the King among them, hoping thereby to have had him eſtabliſhed their Preſbyterian Church-government within this Kingdome, they were very zealous for that part of the Covenant which concernes the preſervation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his Majeſties perſon and authority. Now both the former are forgotten, and they are at this inſtant extreame urgent, and importune for that part of the Covenant which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the reformation of Religion in the three Kingdomes, in doctrine, worſhip, diſcipline and government, according to the word of God, and the example of the beſt reformed Churches: by which words, (the example of, &amp;c.) they would have it granted that their Kirke of Scotland is the beſt reformed in all the world, and therefore we are bound by this clauſe of the Covenant (they conceive) to reforme by their pattern, and to make their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment our example; as if they, (blind Beetles) had attained the very Summum gradum of the government of the Church of Chriſt comprehended in the Goſpell: thus uſing the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant as a Waterman doth his Saile, to turne every way, and hereby they juſtify the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which ſaith, a double minded man is unſtable in all his wayes, Jam. 1. 8. but not one word do they ſpeake for juſtice, or liberty of the Subject, though they ſee all oppreſſion and violence rage and raign amongſt us, this part of the Covenant they lifted up their hands as high to God, and ſwore as ſolemnly to performe, as any other, but becauſe they have no uſe for it, they regard it not: the truth is, they profeſs they know God, but in workes they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him, being abominable, and diſobedient, and to every good worke reprobate.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeake more particularly of our own Preſbyterian Reformers, the Scotiſts of our Kingdome, M. Hollis, Stapleton, and the reſt of the zealous hipocrites, (with their Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prieſts) Covenanters, they ſware you ſee my Friends to endeavour a reformation in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion according to the word of God; and the Parliament as ſeeming to adhere only to this ſure and alone neceſsary and ſufficient rule for reformation, and not to take the bare opinions of men for granted truths, without juſtification from the word of God: to which end they long ſince propounded queries concerning the ſaid government, for the Aſsembly to prove by the word of God, for the juſtification of it: the which queries I have here inſerted, for every mans better information, and conſideration, to wit:</p>
            <p>Firſt, whether the Parochiall, and Congregationall Elderſhips, appointed by Ordinance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:164386:4"/> of Parliament, are jure divino, by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whether all the members of the ſaid Elderſhip, are members thereof, or which of them are, jure divino, and by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Whether the ſupreame Aſsemblyes, or Elderſhips, viz. the Claſſicall, Provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Nationall, whether all, or any of them, or which of them, are jure divino, and by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Whether appeales from congregationall Elderſhips, to the Claſſicall provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and Nationall Aſsemblies, or to any of them, are jure divino, and by the will and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Whether Oecumenicall Aſsemblies, are jure divino, and whether there be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales, from any of the former Aſsemblies to the ſaid Oecumenicall Aſsemblies, jure divino, by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Sixtly, whether by the word of God, the power of judging and declaring what are notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſcandalous offences, and of conventing before them, tryall, and actuall ſuſpending from the Sacrament ſuch offenders accordingly, either in the congregationall Elderſhip, or preſbytery, or in any other Elderſhip, or preſbytery Preſented to the Houſes, as the advice of the Aſsembly, and whether ſuch powers are in them only, or any of them, and in which of them jure divino, and by the will and appointment of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Whether there be any cettaine and particular rules expreſsed in the word of God, to direct the ſaid Elderſhips or Preſbyteries, or any of them in the exerciſe and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the powers aforeſaid, and which are thoſe rules?</p>
            <p>Eightly, is there any thing contained in the word of God, that the Supreame Magiſtracy in a Chriſtian State may not judge and determine what are the aforeſaid notorious and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous offences, and the manner of ſuſpenſion from the ſame, and in what particulars concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the premiſes, are the ſaid Supreame Magiſtracy in the word of God excluded?</p>
            <p>In anſwer of which particulars, the Houſe of Commons deſired of the Aſsembly of divines (falſly ſo called) their proofes from Scripture, and to ſet downe the ſeverall texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the expreſs words of the ſame. And it was alſo ordered that every particular Miniſter of the ſaid Aſsembly, that was, or ſhould be Preſent at the debate of any of theſe queſtions, ſhould upon every reſolution that was to be preſented to the Houſe concerning the ſame, ſubſcribe his reſpective name, either with the affirmative or negative, as he ſhould give his vote; and that they which ſhould diſsent from the major part, ſhould ſet downe their poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive opinions, with the expreſs texts of Scriptures upon which their opinions were groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>Here you ſee an excellent way for the proofe of this Scotiſh creature preſcribed, and a great deale of ſeeming care in the Parliament to ſet up a Religion according to the word of God, and not according to the Church of Scotland: and yet though theſe ſeverall queries or queſtions were by the fallacious Aſsembly never anſwered unto this day, nor are they able to anſwer them ſatisfactorily, for they can neither immediate, or mediate; directly, or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, prove by the word of God, and Goſpell of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, their ſo much preſ'd Preſbiterian government to be jure divine, by divine Law or right, as they moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumtuouſly and andatiouſly have alledged: yet nevertheleſs, although theſe queries were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſolved, nor the Parliament ever ſatisfied by ſufficient proofe out of the word of God, of the lawfulneſs of this government, whether it be the government of Jeſus Chriſt or not; hath this evill party (whereof Mr. Hollis a man ever factious) is reputed chiefe) by their heady preſumptuous courſes, to raiſe to themſelves a faction from London and the Scots, for their owne ſecurity, and to drive on their owne premeditated deſigne of dominion and ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignity, prevailed to have it eſtabliſhed by Ordinance, enjoyning it in all places, and upon all perſons, with as much rigour and ſeverity as ever the Biſhops did their conformity, all which (ye ſee) is directly againſt their Covenant, and no other then plaine perjury: but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they can eſtabliſh this Scotiſh Preſbiterian government, they can never abſolutely eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh tyranny, for the expedients of this Preſbiterian government conduce directly unto ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, even to aboliſh all rules of Law and civill liberty, it is an antipathy to Monarchy, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:164386:4"/> the legall power of civill Magiſtracy, and brings under a yoak (where it is predominant) both King and People (as ſhall God willing be demonſtrated fully in due time) and by this means theſe aſspirers hope through the helpe of the Prieſts to order King Charles, (as the Preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians in Scotland did King James) whom they did reſtraine, affront, diſobey, and raiſe tumults againſt) if he prove refractory to any of their arbitrary Councels; and to ſuppreſs and curb us the free Commoners, that we ſhall not be able either to helpe him, or remedy our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Yet queſtionleſs, if ye aſke any of theſe our maſter Reformers, if when they made and took the Covenant, they did not intend to make Gods word their direct rule of Reformation? They will anſwer, yes: otherwiſe they muſt confeſs themſelves moſt hatefull hipocrites; denying the truth and ſufficiency of the holy Scriptures; men that intend no Religion; but a treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſigne againſt King and People under that notion; and I wiſh it doe not prove ſo in the end by ſome men. If they did intend (as they will not deny) to make Gods word their Rule, to Reforme by: why doe they make the Church of Scotland, the rule of their Reformation, and caſt the word of God behind them? Why doe they enforce upon us the reformation (or rather deformation) of another Kingdome, no waies juſtified or approved by the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and not endeavour (as they have ſworne) ſincerely, to ſeeke out what the good will of the Lord is, concerning his Church, and worſhip, what order and rule he hath preſcribed and left us by his owne Sonne in the Goſpell? Doth not God the Father ſay This is my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Sonne heare <note n="*" place="margin">not the Scots, nor the Prieſts.</note> him: Marke 9. 7. And is it not written, And Moſes truly ſaid unto the Fathers, A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you, like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, him ſhall ye heare in all things whatſoever he ſhall ſay unto you; <note n="*" place="margin">marke &amp; tremble all yee Prieſts &amp; Preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</note> and it ſhall come to paſs, that every ſoule which ſhall not heare that Prophet ſhall be deſtroyed from among the people Acts 3. 22, 23. And doubtleſs, Chriſt who was a Sonne, was not leſs faithfull in Gods houſe then Moſes, who was a ſervant. And againe Yee have a ſure word (ſaith the Apoſtle) unto which yee doe well to take heed: 2 Pet. 1. 19. Yet doe theſe preſumptuous men deſpiſe this command of God, and neglect this ſure word; hearken to their owne corrupt humours, take heed to their owne ambitious covetuous deſires, and ſo proceed in diſpight of God and his Chriſt, to erect a government after their owne inventions: But they will tell you that the Aſsembly have ſearched the Scriptures, and had reſpect to the word, in framing this government: I beleeve they have: but as the Devill did, to make uſe of them for his owne ends, againſt Chriſt; for they did not ſearch to find what government it was the Goſpell did hold out and warrant, and propound and promote that: But they firſt reſolve upon and propound ſuch a government as will ſerve their purpoſe, and then they apply themſelves to make it good by Scriptures, or to enforce the Scriptures for a warrant: thus have they made their forme of Church-government the rule of Gods word, and not Gods word a rule to their forme of government; having done no otherwiſe then many Atournies and Clearkes doe, who often draw Declarations and writings by another mans preſident or pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, without examining or conſulting the Law, in the caſe; which is juſt as if a Taylor ſhould firſt make a Suit, and then make uſe of his meaſure. And grant that this Preſbyteriall government be according to the word of God, is it ſo (in toto?) Is it ſo abſolute that there is no degree of Reformation above it? if ſo, then the Scots have exceedeed that grand planter of Churches, Saint Paul; for he told the Corinthians, That he would yet ſhew them a more excellent way, Cor. 12. 31. And that wee know but in part, and prophecy but in part, but when that which is perfect is come, that which is imperfect ſhall be aboliſhed: 1 Cor. 13. 9, 10. And Saint Peter and the Prophets, ſpake of a new heaven and a new earth, wherein dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth righteouſneſs. Of ſuch a beautifull and perfect Reformation and change, as if it was a new world. 2 Peter 3. 13. and Eſay. 64. 17. I hope no proud Prieſt or Preſbyterian, dare affirme that there is yet any ſuch Reformation or change in Scotland; righteouſneſs dwelleth not there I am ſure: and I would it was not almoſt baniſhed out of England. For as much then as there is a Reformation more true and excellent then theirs (or elſe theirs is none at all) why may not the Independants (ſo called) or ſome others, approach neerer to it then they? with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controverſie, there appeares more of God, and of Chriſt, in the Independants order and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:164386:5"/> waies, then doth in the waies of the Preſbyterians: unleſs the Preſbyterians will affirm themſelves the only wiſe and that the Spirit of the moſt high God, dwels only in them: but then they muſt give me leave to aſke them Saint Pauls queſtion, 1 Cor. 14. 36. Came the word of God out from you? Or came it unto you only? Or did the Biſhops ſeale unto the Preſbyterian Prieſts the holy Spirit, when they ſealed unto them their Ordination, and ſo they have kept it ever ſince cloſe up in a box, to be brought forth in theſe times? Truly (my friends) as learned Rabbies as they are, they erre, not knowing the Scriptures: To the Law (therefore) and to the Teſtimony, if they ſpeake not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them: Iſay. 8. 20. The Devill preached truer doctrine, when he ſaid that Jeſus was the Sonne of God, Mat. 8. 29. then theſe Prieſts when they ſay that the Preſbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an government is jus divinum, the law and government of Jeſus Chriſt; but this is as true as that the Church of Rome is a true Church, the which they doe now <note n="*" place="margin">Mr. Seymour one of the Aſsem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly affirmes it in a diſpute.</note> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, to prove their antichriſtian ſtanding true. And now here by the way I will occaſionally put a few queries.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Whether in caſe a forme of Church-government and worſhip, contrary to the word of God, be by force put upon us, againſt our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, by the Parliament and Preſbyterian Aſsembly: It be not by the ſame reaſon, as lawfull for us to refuſe and reſiſt it (Viet armis,) by force <note n="*" place="margin">And the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe it is enforced by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nation, and without the Kings approbation.</note> as it was for the Scots in like manner, to reject and reſiſt the forme of Church-government, and worſhip put violently upon them againſt their conſciences by the King and Biſhops?</p>
            <p>Secondly, whether the Scots ought, or have any more authority or right, to preſcribe or endeavour an impoſition of Church-government and worſhip upon the People of England, then the People of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land have to preſcribe and endeavour the impoſition of the like upon the People of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If not: Whether the Scots goe not beyond their Laſt? Doe not move out of their ſphere, and intermedle with what they ought not?</p>
            <p>And now ſeeing there is (as cannot be denyed) a more high pitch of Reformation in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and holy worſhip, then is yet attained, or diſcovered; I hope it is no offence nor tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion againſt the State, for any true Chriſtian or ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt to preſs hard after it, and not to conforme himſelfe to fixed formes, bounds and limits, thereby to confine Gods holy Spirit: Yee ſtiffe necked and rebellious (Prieſts) of uncircumciſed hearts and eares, ye have alwaies reſiſted the Holy Ghoſt; as your Fathers (the Biſhops) did, ſo doe yee. Acts 7. 51. I have inſiſted the more upon this particular that the truth herein might be cleare; be cauſe of the great deluſion put upon the People by many of our pretending Reformers, through their grand Oaths and pretexts, of expelling all popery and popiſh innovations, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven whatſoever ſhould be contrary to ſound doctrine (for ſo I underſtand thoſe words in the Proteſtation, contrary to the ſame doctrine) and to reforme Religion according to the word, of God, and to eſtabliſh it in the power and purity of it, and yet notwithſtanding apply all their intereſt and power to ſupport an <note n="*" place="margin">If the ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, what is theirs who ſtand by their ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and power.</note> anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Miniſtery, and to eſtabliſh Church-government, whoſe fruites and effects are nothing but impiety, and hipocriſie; a Religion which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts more in outward formes and Rites, after the manner of Moſes, then in power and piety according to the Goſpell: which conduceth (as appears) more to tyranny, then Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>And ſo I will pretermit their Vowes and Oaths, and come to ſome of their ſpeeches and ſayings: and here I will ſhew you another truth, by the diſcovery of another falſhood, and tracherous vanting act, of the ſame traiterous party or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which ſerves as a patterne, repreſentation, or Image, of the forme of the yoake of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, which (it may be ſuſpected) they ſtudy, and intend to put upon all the Counties and Corporations in the Kingdome, and by which, with the helpe of their determined new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, of Horſe (it is probable) they purpoſe if they can, to ſubjugate the whole Land, and to
<pb facs="tcp:164386:5"/> conforme the People to their arbitrary wils, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to pay, and beare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e and ſuffer, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they ſhall thinke for to enjoyne them, or exact upon them, as well in reſpect of things ſpirituall as civill. In the Parliaments Remonſtrance of the 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of November 1642. Booke Decl. page 700. they tell us, That all Rights or intereſt of publicke truſt, be only for the publicke good, and not for private advantages, (nor to the prejudice of any) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> particular intereſt, much leſs of the publicke. And in May 1642. Booke Decla 172. They call God to witneſs, that the ſafety of the Kingdome, and peace of the people, is their only aime; and becauſe the King would not believe them therein (and well had it been for us if we had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo done) not truſt them wholly therewith, great grew the conteſtation (as yee may well remember) between the King and the Parliament, about the ſetling of the Militia of the Kingdome, and indeed, it was one unhappy cauſe of the quarrell between them. The Parila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then pretending that the King ought not to ſettle it without them, that it behoved them to have the nomination of ſuch perſons as were to be intruſted therewith, in whome they might confide: the Kings affirmes (and they afterwards grant) that the whole power thereof was intruſted by Law in him, for the preſervation and defence of the Kingdome; yet becauſe the King would not paſs the Ordinance in Febn. 1641. for the ſetling it in ſuch forme as they deſired, though the perſons they nominated were not refuſed; they preſently proteſt (I wiſh they were as quicke to doe juſtice, as they are to take exceptions) to diſpoſe of it without him, and accordingly reſolve. (Rebus ſit ſtantibus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> nolenti Regi) that is, they expreſs, In extreame diſtraction, when forreigne forces are probably invited and a malignant popiſh party offended &amp;c. the ordering it to be in them for the (obſerve) preſervation of the Republick, and to prevent the turning the Armes of the Kingdome upon it ſelfe, ſee the Parliaments anſwer to their own queſtion: page hundred and fifty of the Booke of Decl. But I hope the caſe is now altered, for although our diſtractions be ſtill continued by the deſtructive Councels of a pernitious factious party in both Houſes (the heads of which were, and are the cauſe both of thoſe diſtractious and theſe, who like katchers of Eeles, love to fiſh in troubled waters) here is now no feare of invited forreigne forces, and as for that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant popiſh party then ſo much condemned, it is utterly ſubdued and ſuppreſsed; and therefore in all reaſon (rebus nunc ſic ſtantibus) that is) the ſo much feared publicke ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary being long ſince conquered, all viſible danger removed, and the King recovered out of the hands of evill Counſellors, and at preſent with themſelves, and not legally diveſted of his Regall power and right of truſt; in a word, all juſt pretext, and colour of extremity being taken away, they take too much upon them, and abuſe both King and People, who in this opportunity, wherein the royall aſsent may be had, doe diſpoſe of the Militia without him, neither requiring his conſent therein, nor admitting the people according to the Law, to the election of (a thing the King allowed them) the perſons who are to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted, with the diſpoſe and command of their ſtrength and armes, and ſo by conſequence of their eſtates, liberties and lives: I am certaine, in caſe (as God forbid) the royall Throne ſhould by exigent become void, the Parliament are not their owne Maſters, not can by the fundamentall Law and conſtitution of this Kingdome, diſpoſe of us the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of England, and our power, armes, or intereſt, without our conſents; how much leſs at this inſtant: All the Commons of England have more juſt ground of jealouſe from them in now ſo doing, and of complaint and accuſation againſt that malevolent ill-affected party among them, by whoſe power and influence it hath beene effected, conſidering the perſons unto whom the Militia and ſtrength of the Kingdome, is in divers places of late committed, then the Parliament ever had from and againſt the King, for refuſing onely to grant it in their way and manner: for they choſe the perſons, and he approved them; but the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are herein both chooſers and approvers (as in many things, many of them are both Judge and Witneſs) though we neither approve, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> wee, as well as the King, are in this particular debarred by them, of our rights and priviledge: but this is not the greateſt detriment we ſuſtaine, and are likely without prevention to ſuffer, and which this predominant malicious party intends, hereby: for doe but caſt your eye, and ſee and conſider what perſons are put out of the Militia; and what perſons are continued, admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:164386:6"/> and intruſted, and yee will preſently judge by a little what the whole meanes For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, firſt for an introduction, the pretended Lord Major, Aldermen, and Common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, muſt petition in the name of the City, though the City never propounded it to them, to have the Militia ſetled in their own hands, (at they had formerly) and why not then to have it by their Charter, but by Ordinance for a certain time? and this by the power and prevalency of the malevolent party is forthwith obtained, becauſe it tends to their predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, tyrannous ends: approved Alderman Pennington, who ſtood in the breach when they all were affraid, whoſe fidelity and ability was throughly experimented, at ſuch time when as the winds blew higheſt, and the ſtormes grew ſtrongeſt; a man adjudged by the City wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be their Parliament man, and by the Parliament worthy to be Lieutennant of the Tower of London, is now no longer worthy to be intruſted with the Militia, but turned out as a man ſuſpected; ſo are the Aldermen KFoulk, Weaver and Kenrick, Col. Wilſon, though a member of the Houſe, alſo Col. Player, Tichburn, and others: And why? they are not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute for the Faction; they were opoſite to Bunce, and Beliamy, the Court of Aldermen and Common Councell, in the proſecution of their laſt indirect, illegall, and factious Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance and Petition; by which meanes they diſcovered themſelves opponants to their Scotch deſign of Preſbyterie, and therefore they are not any longer to be confided in, or fit to have the command of any power: howſoever they had a parcell of dry thanks from the Houſe for their former fidelity and paines: it is better I confeſs then a Priſon (as Lilburn, Tuleday, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon, Nichols, and multitudes more have had) for their good ſervice. Yet I muſt tell them, it is but after the old manner of the Court, who uſed to put a man off with an hypocriticall complement, when they had no further occaſion to uſe him, or were deſirous to be quit of him: and it is obſerved, that empty thanks is a ſufficient reward from the Houſe, for any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, though his ſervice hath been never ſo good, and ſuperlative, unleſs they have ſome other deſign or ingagement upon him: but to Knaves and fooles they have been very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and free, (witnes the 10. l. given to the two Officers that brought up Enſign Nichols; &amp; the arreares lately ordered to be paid two great ones, for diſcovering two great lyes: by which you may ſee, they can pay whom they liſt, and whom they liſt they will not:) I could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance you ſome examples of late, and their own neſts are generally ſo well feathered, that many, or moſt of them are almoſt ſmothered, they can neither ſee, heare nor ſpeake. Alas poore Commons of England, your backs in the meane time are left bare and naked! But to proceed; marke what honeſt men are continued, put in, and intruſted with the Militia, for the honeſt men that are put out and diſtruſted: Aldermen, Bance, Adams, Langham, (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man of knowledge can read them) Colonels, Weſt, and Bellamy, the one an oppreſſive Goaler, the other an arrogant Mag-pye, and Bromfield that ran away at Newberry: the Lord Major Sir John Geere, who was plundered for his 20th. and 5th. part, who maliciouſly cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvents men, that he may like the devill take them in a ſnare, and then impriſons them, contrary to law, (as he did Maſter Tew, and then ſent his Marſhall to apprehend him without a Warrant) a hopefull Magiſtrate, and fit to be intruſted with the publique Sword, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of the Lawes, and defence of the Subjects juſt Rights and Libertyes: and that Sir John Woolaſton, who by the Law is more worthy to be arraigned before a Bench of Aſſize for buying ſtoln <note n="*" place="margin">It is truth and when time ſerves will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> Plate of the Kings, then to ſit upon the Bench of Judgement to oppreſs and do injuſtice, as his common practiſe is, or to be intruſted with the Militia; for it is contrary to all principles of reaſon, that a Magiſtrate, or publique Miniſter, who is unjuſt to the People in his place or practiſe, will ever be faithfull to them in time of trouble or diſtreſs, or defend either them or their liberties, whenſoever they are aſsayled; the Hawke will as ſoon defend the Dove, and the Kite the Chickens: this is that Sir John Woolaſton, who right or wrong commits all to Newgate that come before him, for the benefit of his brother the head Goaler there; who is as diligent to ſtarve and deſtroy them when he hath them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der cuſtody, (as he did one Sparks lately, and hath done many more) as the other is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them. As for Alderm-Gibbs of the Militia, he hath a good ſtock of money in the name of his Sonne, beyond the Seas, he need not care which way the world goes; good Sir John
<pb facs="tcp:164386:6"/> Woolaſton and he, had their ſingers both in one Pye; I hope they lick'd them cleane, and themſelves (like Bullocks) fat, though they have lickt others leane: their ſilver tongue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit them well in Rylees buſines, and they have you know been eſteemed honeſt and truſty ever ſince: I could read you a character of moſt of them, but to avoid prolixity I will now forbeare till a more convenient time: and will only tell you what I apprehend to be the end of this ſudden, and ſo happy ſettlement of the Militia of London; the effect and what you may expect by it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By this meanes, the Earle of Mancheſter, M. Hollis, Stapleton, Earle ſenior, and the reſt of this nayterous faction; who have occaſioned the violation of all our Lawes and Libertyes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed their truſt; and are the chiefe obſtructers of the courſe of juſtice, and redreſs of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances; promoters of all evill councels, and the cauſe of the continuince of all our troubles and diſtractions; who among other things drive a deſign to ſave their own Stakes, and ſecure their own lives; for that they know they are for theſe things lyable to queſtion, and abnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to juſtice, do conceive they have well ſecured themſelves from all invaſion, by petition or cry for juſtice againſt them, from any party within the City.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they ſhall by this meanes the more eaſily erect their new formed Monſter of preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie; for what they cannot perſwade, they will inforce, and who (thinke they) now dare, or can reſiſt it?</p>
            <p n="3">3. They conceive they ſhall eaſily ſuppreſs the independent party (as they terme them) and divert them from petitioning for Law and liberty, to both which theſe vile men are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together averſe; and that if they do notwithſtanding, continue ſuch their petitioning, yet may they the more ſecurely deny and diſtaſte their petitions, and punniſh their perſons: for is not the Militia in their hands? and if they will not ſubmit like ſlaves, but beginne to ſtir and ſtruggle; then the Militia is ready to oppoſe them as Rebels and Traytors, although they challenge but right and juſtice, of their ſervants, who are many of them become Traytors: and this is apparent by their late declaring their high diſpleaſure againſt that juſt petition, &amp; the Petitioners, for divers points of liberty and juſtice, which was preferred by a multiude of well affected Citizens: firſt it was intercepted and anticipated, contrary to the courſe of Parliaments, and the liberty of the Subject, by the meanes of Recorder Glin, (who hath ſhewed more favour to Captain <note n="*" place="margin">Evans wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully killed a man, and being brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder, he baſely reviled the poore widow, and freed the murtherer.</note> Thomas Evans, a notorious murderer, then ever he did to poor Orphans, for whom he ſhould have been a juſt Advocate) witneſs the Orphans of M. Bury, againſt whom he tooke Fees (if not bribes) by which meanes (notwithſtanding many petitions, and as many faire promiſes from the then temporizing Lord major Adams, and others of that Orphan de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Faction) the ſaid Orphans to this day can obtain no juſtice, nor part of their fathers perſonal eſtate, unleſs they will take fourſcore for foure hundred pounds, and thus are the poore Orphans miſerably ruin'd having ſpent the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of their annuall revennue for five yeares together, to obtain juſtice, but by the corruption of Brigandine (who ſquares his actions by his Maſters Rule) and power of the Recorder who is the Executors friend, nothing can be done,; all paſsages are blockt up; honeſt men dare not ſpeake, and knaves will not, &amp; ſo the poore orphans are left altogether remidileſs:) but to proceed, the aforeſaid Petition being referred to a Committee, and the Citizens put off with faire words, till this grand Ordinance for the Militia was paſsed, and then preſently they thundered as if the Petition had tended to the prejudice of Church and State.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If they want money, or a new Army to ſecure themſelves, that old Aſse the City muſt raiſe men, or ſend out their trained Bands for them; and the poore Commons of London muſt pay and beare, or elſe be plundered, and what remedy; and whatſoever the Parliament will exact, and the Military men execute, the Commons of London muſt obey and ſubmit to, though never ſo unjuſt a tax, or impoſition: But you will ſay, the trained Bands will not be all of a mind; but this Party having prevailed to new Modelling of the Commiſſioners, you ſhall ſee them new Model the train Bands alſo, and here is the firſt piece of the frame of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands ſlavery; &amp; muſt ſerve (if they can carry it) for a leading caſt unto the whole Kingdome.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:164386:7"/>
            <p>The effects (yee Commons of London) which yee may expect hence, are the vtter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition of your free elections of your Mayors, Aldermen, Sheriffs, Common-councell men, and other publick Officers, of your body and Corporation, ſo that now ye may bid all you priviledges, adue, and the free, borne Apprentices after ſeaven yeares hard ſervitude, <note n="*" place="margin">Marke yee Apprentices.</note> expect a perpetuall vaſsalage; by this meanes the hopes yee had of the recovery of ancient Rights and immunities are ſruſtrate, and yee (after all your coſts and adventures for your liberties) become the firſt abſolute ſlaves in England, if God doe not otherwiſe prevent, or raiſe up ſome Othniel, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hud, Shamger, Barak, or Gideon to deliver you. And in ſuch hands as theſe, this deſperate domineering faction; by all ſymptomes and ſignes, purpoſe to ſettle the Militia, in all the Counties and Corporations of the Kingdome and have already in Durham, Cumberland, and other places northward, put it principally into their hands, who are declared Traytors and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to the State, Malignants and Delinquents, ſome of which have been actually in warre againſt the Parliament and their Country, as Sir George Vane, old Sir Henryes Sonne, who was in armes with the King, and is now made one of the Deputy Lieutenants of the Militia for Durham, a Juſtice of Peace, and a Committee-man, and yet ſcarce good commodity for the hang-man, S. Wilfrid Lawſon of Cumberland ſuch another, yet by the prevalency of this party, intruſted with the poſse-Commitatus, whereby he may raiſe the County, and cut all honeſt mens throats, if he imagine cauſe: To tell you of the commands and power where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Lieutenant Col. Offeere, Cap. Muſgrave,, Story, Stoddert, and divers others are inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and intruſted in thoſe parts, who have beene in armes againſt the Parliament and their Country, to the great trouble, hazard, and affliction of all the faithfull and wel-affected there, beſides many others in other places of the Land, would be to tedious; let theſe for preſent ſuffice for example: And all, rather then to truſt the honeſt and approved in the Land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are contrary to their treaſonable deſignes and practices, and will not ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves nor the Country to become their vaſsals and pack-horſes. I wiſh thoſe Northern Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries had no juſt cauſe of complaint againſt that deceitfull double dealing. Lord Wharton, I will for ſpeciall cauſe (not that I fear or regard him, or any man, farther then he is ſincere and vertuouſly honourable) ſpare him; but it it is good both for him and others to repent, and doe their firſt workes, leſt a worſe thing befall them; there is nothing hid, but it may be made manifeſt, to runne away from a fight for feare, is tollerable, and is contingent to the greateſt <note n="*" place="margin">Witnes Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Leſhley.</note> Generall, but for a profeſsed Souldier of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to turne his back and flee from the truth, is to be abhorred. Hath not Chriſt ſaid, He will be aſhamed of ſuch, when he ſhall come in his Fathers glory with the holy Angels? Marke 8. 38. And did Jehoſaphat proſper, that tooke part with Ahab? Or did ever any eſcape by iniquity? And if Meroz was curſed, yea, bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly curſed, becauſe they would not helpe, what are they that doe hurt? and are not they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo curſed (though they be doing) that doe Gods worke negligently; Conſider theſe things ſeriouſly all yee that are ſunke and ſetled upon the lees, all ye Neuters and indifferent ones, that plead moderation, non-ſeaſon, and prudence, for your baſeneſs of Spirit, negligence, and cowardice, in the great cauſe of God, and this diſtreſsed Kingdome, and yee (Timidi) yee fearefull ones, who are more afraid of the face and diſpleaſure of man, whoſe breath is in his noſtrels, and whoſe councels periſh, then of the power and wrath of God, Who is a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, and whoſe councels abide forever: That feare more the looſing of your places and profits, then the loſing of Gods favour and countenance, and the peace of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Read that 21. Rev. 8. and tremble, remember your ſelves, rouſe up your ſpirits, and ſhew your ſelves couragious for truth and juſtice, and zealous for the glory of the Lord of Hoſts; if yee will not, know that deliverance will come to Gods People ſome other way, and yee ſhall not eſcape. As for M. Hollis and others, whoſe councels and practices tend princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to treaſon and tyranny, injuſtice, and violence (I know what I ſay, and doubt not yet but in time to ſee it proved ſo) who live without Law, and act contrary to Law, like tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Rebels: Let ſuch men know, that God will render unto them according to their workes; and I am confident, that they ſhall never be able to accompliſh their wicked enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize,
<pb facs="tcp:164386:7"/> and that the pit they have digged for others, they ſhall fall into themſelves. God will take them by their own counſels, as he did in old time, Achitophell, and Haman; and as he did Strafford, and Canterbury, in theſe dayes: yea, in thoſe two preſidents, they have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared a halter for their owne necks, and their owne words ſhall be their Judges: Strafford, and Canterbury were condemned for treaſonable councels and ſpeeches, endeavours, and intentions of ſubverting the fundamentall Lawes, and frame of government, and of ſetting up an arbitrary power, and rule of government: And whether Hollis and others, his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous complices, have not been, (not only the intenders and indevourers, but) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all authors and actours of theſe things, I doe appeale to all inteligent men, who have taken any cognizance of their councels and actions? So that if the King (as it is a queſtion) did want juſt matter of occaſion in his charge of treaſon againſt M. Hollis, and others in 1641. both he and the whole Kingdome may without much ſearch, find enough doubtleſs at this time; yea, have not M. Hollis and others, his complices and confederates, not onely verifyed many or moſt of thoſe <note n="*" place="margin">Read &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them, and compare them with their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, B. Decla. page 34.</note> articles of Treaſon and miſdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours; but alſo augmented and exceeded them in many things? I could (but at preſent for ſpeciall reaſons will not) particularize: in the mean time, (my friends) make uſe of your owne obſervations, call your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories to account, and compare things with things, adviſe well, make your ſelves ſtrong, and feare not. Why ſhould the old Engliſh proverb (for our love and faithfulneſs) be made true upon us? Save a traytor or theefe from the gallowes, and he ſhall be the firſt that ſhall hang you: indeed we are neer it, if wee doe not beſtir our ſelves and prevent it: But it is better that a few preſumptuous men, whoſe Lucifer-like pride and ambition, hath lifted them up to Heaven, ſhould be caſt down into oblivion and darkneſs, then the whole Nation periſh.</p>
            <p>And therefore yee free Commoners of England up quickly, and looke about you; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeriouſly the ſnare prepared for you, and compare the vehement endeavours of theſe trayterous perſons, to diſband the Army, (which hath fought and is reſolved to ſtand for your liberties) with this their patterne, and firſt piece of thraldome, in ſetling the Militia thus at this time in ſuch mens hands in London, and their putting power into the hands of ſuch as are enemies to the publicke in the Country; and ſee if theſe men intend any thing to you, and yours but bondage and ſlavery, and this is part of that ye are told in the <note n="*" place="margin">Both worth your notice.</note> books called the Warnings for all the Counties of England, and the New found Stratagem upon the Petition of Eſsex. Be vigilent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and aſſiſtant to keep the Army on foot, for your owne defence, and preſervation of your ſelves, your eſtates and liberties, Country, and poſterities, from inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricable vaſsalage, and irrecoverable ruine; for that once downe, this ambitious party, who aime at Soveraignity, to make the King their ſcorne, and us their ſlaves, will preſently not only turne the Militia in every place upon the Country, (as they have already deſigned in the City) but raiſe horſe alſo after the manner of Germany, in all Counties of the Kingdome for the better ſecuring themſelves, and this their forme of tyranny, and if ſuch men be not traytors who be? Where ſhal we find any? and if this be to imploy their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke truſt, for the <note n="*" place="margin">Book Decl. page 700.</note> publicke good, and whether their <note n="†" place="margin">Page 172.</note> onely alme, be herein the Kingdomes ſafety and the peoples peace, as they have declared and ſpoken, let all England judge? And thus yee ſee they falcify their words and Declarations, as well as breake their Oaths and Proteſtations: but in their Booke of Declarations page 207. they ſay, That in caſe of extreame danger, and his Majeſties refuſall to ſettle the Militia of the Kingdome, the Ordinance, (that is the Ordinance which was then made in that time of ſuch extreame danger) agreed upon by both Houſes for the Militia, doth oblige the people, and ought to be obeyed by the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome, but now (bleſsed be God) here is no ſuch caſe of extreame danger, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath the King been ſo much as petitioned, or ſought unto for this Ordinance of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia of London, and therefore it doth not bind the People, nor can they by the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Lawes of the Land, be compelled to obey it, beſides they ordering the Militia to the
<pb facs="tcp:164386:8"/> publicke hurt, and not to the publicke good, contrary to the intent and equity of the law, and the end of their truſt, the people are (ipſo facto) diſcharged of their obedience to their Ordinance, for wee are not bound to obey to our own damage and deſtruction; ſee this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by their owne diſtinction and argument in Book of Decl. page 150. But to make a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcovery of the truth, by diſcovering more of this evill Parties falſhoods, breach of truſt, and traiterous practices againſt us: take notice, that in the Booke of Declarations pa. 720. the Parliament declare, That it is the liberty and priviledge of the People, to petition unto them, for the eaſe and redreſs of their grievances and oppreſſions, and that they are (marke) bound in duty to receive their Petitions: here is a faire acknowledgment; but I pray you marke their actions: many thouſand honeſt and really affected to the publicke li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, in the City, had prepared a petition to have beene preſented to the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, for redreſs of ſome grievances and oppreſſions, and reſtoration of ſome liberties and priviledges, comprehending nothing but things legall and juſt, what they ought to grant: this Petition, contrary to all courſe of Parliament and the liberty of the Subject, was by the power and ſubtilty of the aforeſaid faction or party, (who have their ſetting dogges and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles to diſcry and hunt for them) intercepted (as thus they anticipated the Armies Petition) before it was perfected, and made ready to be preſented, the copy of it was read in the Houſe, and referred to a Committee (whereof fierce fiery M. Lee was Chaire-man) to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and report it (they did not ſo by the factious Petition and Remonſtrance framed by the pretended Lord Mayor and common councell men) againſt which they then nor finding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny juſt cauſe of exception, held the vowchers thereof with faire words in hopes of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, untill they had mounted their late new Ordinance of the Militia for London, and then they declared their diſtate and diſpleaſure againſt it; the which injuſt dealing, and violation of our native liberty and priviledge, the Petioners not brooking, preſented a Petition to the Houſe of Commons for juſtice and redreſs, and deſire that their former Petition might not be cenſured before it was in due order preſented, hereupon Hollis, Stapleton, and the reſt of that faction (traytours to their Country) according to their uſuall courſe through their malignant influence prevalency, procured this latter Petition to be voted ſeditious, and that both it and the former ſhould be burnt by the hands of the hang man (was there ever ſuch a thing done before by a Parliament in England, ſure not) and that to queſtion any act done in the Houſe, was a breach of the priviledges of Parliament: but by cunning to intetcept the former Petition, and tyrannically to ſuppreſs and reject it, and illegally to impriſon ſome of the Petitioners for it (as they have done M. Tue, and M. Browne) was no breach of the priviledge of the ſubject? No, deare friends and fellow Commoners, unleſs ye have (like fooles) reſolved with your ſelves, after ſo ſharpe and bloody a conteſtation, for your Law, and your liberties, to relinquiſh, your claime by Magna Charta, and the good old Law; and to hold your lives and liberties, and all you have, by the Arbitrary Votes of the Houſe of Commons, and to become Tenants at will, unto a company of traytors, and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants: Vp in Gods name, up, demand redreſs, and vindicate your ſelves, and native rights, againſt Votes, and Voters, (hodie mihi, cras tibi) what theſe men doe, to this or that parte, or place of the Kingdome, and people to day, they may and will doe to another parte or place to morrow. And they have injuſtly refuſed more then a few (as that of the Counties of Bunckinham and Hereford, and divers others from all parts) petitioners for redreſs of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and granting of liberties already, and in this late particular preſident, is the very eſsence and end of a Parliament perverted; the rights of Parliament, and the ancient courſe of Parliamentary proceedings ſubverted, and our native rights and priviledges, ſo much as lies in this diſtructive party, wholy vacated and deſtroyed. And whether this ſtrange Vote and fact, doe not juſtifie the fifth article exhited by the King againſt Hollis and others 1641. (Book Decl. page 35.) by which he chargeth them, To have trayterouſly endeavoured, to ſubvert the very rights and beings of Parliaments? I beſeech you all yee lovers of Englands liberties, conſider, and judge: And alſo part of that firſt ſeaventh Article exhibitted by the Houſe againſt the Earle of Strafford. Yea, conſider I beſeech you, compare and ſee, if the words, waies councels, and practices, of the Earle of Mancheſter, Hollis, Stapleton, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb facs="tcp:164386:8"/> their complices and confederates, doe not fully anſwer the 1, 2 5. and Part of the 6. Article exhibited in 1641. by the King: and to the firſt, and part of the 2, 3, 4 6, &amp; 7. Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and ſome others (only mutatis mutandis) which were exhibited by the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, againſt Strafford and alſo to ſome which were exhibited againſt Canterbury, even as face anſwereth to face, in water? Truly wee are no longer free, but abſolute ſlaves already: if wee may not Petition for our liberty, what? unleſs wee will firſt aſke them what we ſhall petition, we muſt not it ſeems at all petition? Away with ſuch Traytors from the Earth.</p>
            <p>This Act and Vote, anſwers thoſe trayterous ſpeeches of Harvy and Solloway, two cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt men of the Houſe of Commons, who impudently ſaid, (note) That the Parliament might doe what they would, and were not to be queſtioned for it. One of the Articles of high treaſon charged upon the Earle of Strafford, was, as appeares in the fourth article of his ſecond impeachment or accuſation) that he ſhould declare and ſay, That Ireland was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Nation, and that the King might doe with them what he pleaſed; and is not here as much ſpoken, and more by theſe two trayterous ſpirits, Harvy and Solloway? For Ireland was indeed a Nation by us conquered, and his ſpeech related to the King, who was their head, and had a Power over them: but theſe mens words are ſpoken of us a free People, who though formerly conquered, yet have long ſince redeemed our liberties with our ſwords, and relate to a company of men, who are but ſubjects, and the Kingdomes ſervants, only cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and choſen to councell and adviſe; not to reigne and tyrannize. But let us argue it, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Courts in the Land whatſoever, have rules of juriſdiction and limmits, and hath the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Court of Parliament none? It is very unreaſonable even againſt all rule of reaſon, that, that Court which preſcribes rules to all other Courts, ſhould be without all rule it ſelfe. The Lord chiefe Juſtice Cook, in his treatiſe of the juriſdiction of the high Court of Parliament declares, and proves otherwiſe: and I am certaine that it is againſt the very conſtitution and being of it. for there is both <note n="*" place="margin">See Cooks Inſtituts, Rotu. Parli.</note> (Lex &amp; confuetudo Parliamenti) both a Law and a cuſtome, or uſage of Parliament, Beſides there is a fundamentall Law of the Land, againſt which the Parliament cannot (that is lawfully as a Parliament) act, for whatſoever act is made or done in Parliament that is contrary to Magna Charta, is void, no Law, and not to be <note n="*" place="margin">See 42. Ed. 3. chap. 1.</note> obeyed (and what force then if well examined are moſt of our preſent Parliament Votes. Orders and Ordinances?) by which it is evident that the Parliament is not <note place="margin">* But new Lords new laws.</note> without a law and rule, nor may doe what they will, nor any thing (onely in caſe of extremity, and then alſo for good of the publicke, and not unto example) contrary to the fundamentall Lawes and conſtitutions of the Kingdome. And was not one Wentworth of the Houſe of Commons queſtioned, yea, and committed in the daies of queen Elizabeth, for his words and deeds in the Houſe? And can they themſelves deny but that for Treaſon, fellony, and breach of the Peace, they are queſtionable? By all which it is cleare, that the proudeſt of them may be queſtioned, and is accountable for any miſdemeanour, or illegall unjuſt act done by them within the Houſe. They ſay to queſtion them for any thing out of the Houſe, is a breach of their priviledge: and muſt we queſtion them neither in the Houſe? What is a Parliament man lawlels? Neither without nor within? there is a new priviledge (as their Ordinances are a new manner of Lawes) it was not ſo of old. The King who is the Supreame head, is not without the Law, he may not doe what he liſt: Sure then much leſs may they, who are but ſubjects and only councellers not Commanders, Servants not Maſters. But is not this ſtrange doctrine, my friends, that a Parliament man muſt not be queſtioned for whatſoever he doth in the Houſe? Lo here is a new hidra-headed prerogative, for you to ſuppreſs, which yee never expected. Lop it betimes: for this poſition, tends directly to the ſubverſion of all our Lawes and liberties, and the exaction of an arbitrary rule over us. And if this Vote Be not treaſonable what is? For by this rule they may within the Houſe, conſult, contrive and act, high treaſon, againg King, and Kingdome, commit murder, pick pockets, and breake the peace, deviſe and conſpire to deſtroy and maſsacre us, to robbe and ſpoyle us, and not to be queſtioned: becauſe it was reſolved, and done within the Houſe. Brave Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary principles!</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:164386:9"/>
            <p>Is it not more then high time fellow Commoners to rouze up our ſpirits, and beſtir us to to bring ſuch as are the authors and promoters of theſe, and ſuch like deſtructive comands and actions to condigne punniſhment? ſhall not the Judge of all the world (ſaith Abraham) do right? and ſhall not the Court of Courts, the ſupreame Court of all the Kingdome (we may ſay) do right? Woe is to us, for lamentable is our caſe; our ſtreame muſt needs be puddle &amp; dirt, when our very fountain is filthy and corrupt: (Corruptio optima eſt peſſima) that which is beſt, being corrupted is the worſt: that which was formerly Englands Balſum and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote, is now become Englands greateſt Coros;ive and poyſon: yet not in it ſelfe; but by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, through the boundles ambition, and inſatiable avarice of an company of trayterous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in both houſes of Parliament; the chiefe of which are Mancheſter, and Stamford, Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and Hollis, Merrick, and ſome others; who have runne themſelves by their wicked deeds againſt the King and Common Wealth, into a deſperate condition; and therefore endeavour by all meanes to bring the Land into a confuſion, and ſo to make our latter end worſe then our beginning: This Stapletons Speech verifies, who lately ſaid, (It is now come to this, that either we muſt ſinke them, (meaning the Army) and their friends, or they ſinke us;) unto this end it ſeemes they have ſo highly provoked the Army: For prevention of which cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and to procure our ſelves eaſe and remedy, we muſt take them away, charge them home and demand their perſons to be delivered up to juſtice: why feare we? what power hath any Parliament man, that he hath not received from them that choſe him? And if a King ſo ſoon as he ceaſeth to rule by the known Law, doth degenerate into a Tyrant, and is worthy to be ejected; what are thoſe Parliament men, Mancheſter, Hollis, Stapleton and others of this Faction, who have ſo probably, contrary to their Oathes, truſts, and duties, left all rule of Law and Juſtice, and by their power and prevalency have dealt with us, and diſpoſed of our eſtates and libertyes, after their own wicked, crooked wills? and what are theſe men worthy of according to law and reaſon? expulſion is too little, and beheading is too honourable: But happily ſome of them may ſay by me, becauſe I declare that which they can no wayes colour, that I am mad; I am ſure they are, and their madnes doth appeare to all men, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſome of them would not have ſo baſely reproached his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax (who came to London only becauſe of his diſeaſe, and ſtaid there a while for his infirmity and weakenes) in ſaying it was fitter for him to be with his Army, which is in a diſtemper, then to be in Hide Parke courting of Ladies. If the Army be diſtempered, hath not Mancheſter, Stapleton, Hollis, and that turbulent faction diſtempered them, by their im-parliamentary Declaration againſt them, and ingratefull abuſe of them? Nay do they not diſtemper and trouble the Parliament, and whole Kingdome? are not they the only obſtructers of our ſetle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in England, and of the reliefe of diſtreſsed Ireland? are not theſe I ſay the cauſe of all our diſtraction and diſturbance? I wiſh they were not; and as for Sir Thomas his courting of Ladies, I would Sir Peter Temple, Sir John Merrick, Sir John Hipſly, M. Moyle, Moore, Bell, Bowyer, and too many more among them, did not more court Harlots, viſit Whores, and exerciſe drunkennes, <note n="*" place="margin">Foth what a ſtinke is here.</note> and other baſenes, then honourable Sir Thomas, worthy man doth delight in courting of Ladies? I do remember when the Earle of Eſsex, and his chiefe commanders, Merrick, (one of the trayterous crew) and the reſt, came to London, to laze, ſmoake tobacco, and <note place="margin">Oh ſweet Reformers.</note> drinke Sack, court, complement, vaunt and vapour of that they never did, and a potent enemy at hand in the field, who came up to Brainford, to the hazzard Army and Citie before they were diſcovered, and no chiefe Officer there, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">of the whole</note> to command, or deliver forth * Ammunition: and when not only the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall but all the chiefe officers, while there was a deſtroying enemy in power <note place="margin">Thanks falſe Merrick, thou didſt the like and worſe at Edge-hill.</note> abroad, came and ſtaid their own time in London, to revell, ramble, and rore, drink, domineere, and whore; while the ſouldier was left without reſtriction or order, to range, raven, and plunder, ſpoyle and make waſte, at Saint Albans, and in the Country thereabouts, and no complaint made of diſtemper, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, either by the Houſe or any of their Members: but the Proverb is, that ſome may better ſteale a Horſe, then others looke over the hedge. If Sir Thomas his officers
<pb facs="tcp:164386:9"/> or ſouldiers were like wicked Col. Graves, then this evill Faction might ſay they were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered indeed: yet this lewd ſhameles man is Stapletons only Minion, and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall inſtrument, (as truly moſt fit for their wicked purpoſe) in the Army, for this mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, malevolent party: but theſe men like Toads are ſo big ſwoln with pride and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite, that they are ready to burſt; and their poyſon will never be purged out, nor we freed from the diffuſed venome of it, till ſome of them be highly exalted, and made an example. Take away the wicked from the King (ſaith Solomon) and his Mhrone ſhall be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in righteouſnes: take away the wicked and trayterous out of both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Parliament ſhall be upright, and proſper, and wee poore Commons be ſoone eſtabliſhed in peace and happyneſs.</p>
            <p>In the Booke of Declarations, pag. 207. they ſeem to cleare themſelves of a charge laid upon them by the King, ſaying: That there was no colour, that they went about to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce a new Law, much leſs to exerciſe <note n="*" place="margin">Marke.</note> an arbitrary power, but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it. How true this tax or charge hath ſince proved, let the whole Land judge, and their own actions witneſs: for if they have not brought in a new Law, I am ſure they have made no uſe of the old, unleſs it hath been for evill. And whether they have exerciſed an Arbitrary power, I need not aske the queſtion, for it is paſt doubt or ſcruple. But they ſay in the ſame Declaration, That this Law is as old as the Kingdome, To wit, That the Kingdome muſt not be without a meanes to preſerve it ſelfe: It is well (yet truly grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.) By their own principle you ſee, the naturall or reall body politique, in caſe the Repreſentative, or virtuall faile, and deceive their truſt, <note n="*" place="margin">Marke and make uſe of it.</note> hath power to preſerve it ſelfe: Marke yee free Commons of England, here is a ſure ground for yee to ſtand on, yee are not yet paſt hope, nor deſtitute of meanes of helpe: therefore cheare up your ſpirits, and quit your ſelves like men: imploy ahd improve your juſt powers, for the preſervation of your ſelves againſt all thoſe ſelfe-ſeeking, ambitious, trayterous, tyrannicall ſpirits in both Houſes; who have forſworn themſelves, betrayd their truſt, and imployed all their power and intereſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with yee intruſted them, for your good and ſafety, to your woe and miſety: And yee faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the Houſe of Commons, whoſe hearts have ever been upright, (although yee have been awed, and overpowred) to God, your King, and Country; beware of theſe ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, who would involve you in the ſame treaſonable works with them, that ſo they like Pick-pockets, may the better ſcape in a crowd unſeen: rather proteſt againſt them, and their proceedings; and declare them to the Kingdome, ſerve them as they have ſerved o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: thus ye will acquit your ſelves of jealouſies, and guilt, diſcharge your truſt and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and endeare your ſelves to your Countryes: otherwiſe you muſt expect to ſuffer as partakers, and to undergo the cenſure of confederates, and compactours: Sure and ſtable is this principle, (Salus Populi eſt ſuprema Lex, The welfare and ſafety of the People is the ſupream Law: and therefore where this end is by Truſtees perverted or neglected, the People by the Law of nature have power to preſerve and ſecure themſelves: and as certain is that Rule, that (Major qui facit, quam quod fit: He which makes is greater then that which is made; and therefore is to be preferred: and in caſe that which is made prove uſeleſs, hurtfull, or unprofitable, he which makes hath power to modifie, reſtraine, remove, or nullifie, even as ſeemeth good unto him, and may moſt conduce to his good and benefit: And therefore in caſe we cannot receive juſtice from the Parliament, let us force our powers, and apply our ſelves my friends and fellow Commoners, to have juſtice upon the Authors of our injuſtice and oppreſſions? and no longer ſtand ſtill like People without life and ſpirit, and ſuffer our juſt and reaſonable demands and tequeſts to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſted and deſpiſed, as dung or dirty our Petitions for liberty and juſtice, to be illegally
<pb facs="tcp:164386:10"/> cenſured and ſentenced to be burnt as ſome horrid, treaſonable and blaſphemous opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or papers, and our neighbours friends, and fellow Commoners, to be tyrannical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impriſoned: and barbarouſly uſed before our eyes, for ſtanding up in the behalfe of the Kingdome, and petitioning for our native and lawfull rights and liberties; by a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate wicked party of falſe perfidious men in both Houſes, Machivilians and Traytors: whoſe Votes and Councels, waies and workings, tend only to ſecure their guilty carcaſes from juſtice, and to enſlave and deſtroy us, and our rights and freedomes, who have no feare of the Lord before them, nor any compaſſion or tender reſpect to their native Country this diſtreſsed Nation.</p>
            <p>And now yee grave and wealthy Citizens of the Preſbyterian faction, whoſe eyes are ſwolne with fatneſse, and whoſe hearts with pride and ambition: Who happily according to the generall fortune of the great men of London, are endued with a greater portion of riches, ſtate and preſumption, then of prudence, integrity or wiſdome: Give me leave to tell you an Itinerant ſtory, or a paraboricall tale of two Travellers: There were two Travellers met upon the road, and paſsed friendly along time in ſilence together; at length they diſcover to each other whether they are going, and the end and intention of their travell, and the way, they would walke, and they agreed both in one mind, and upon one thing, and ſo they ratifie their aſsociation and friend-ſhip: but the one was not only wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but -ore weakned (at leaſt he ſo appeared) both in ſtrength and purſe, by reaſon of his long journy and the many difficulties and dangers, he had already incountered, and overcome; and very knowing was hee of the way that was yet to be travelled, and of the dangers and difficulties which would oppoſe them therein, before they ſhould come to their journies end: the other albeit he had come as farre, yet by reaſon he was through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well furniſhed and provided of moneies and all needfull ſupplies at his firſt ſetting forth did retaine the more ability and ſtrength, and had the moſt monies for his ſupport throughout: but alas he was not ſo knowing in the way, nor skilfull as the other, to avoid the dangers therein: whereupon he promiſeth the other aſſiſtance with his purſe, and ſtrength, to carry him through all ſtraits, till they come to their journies end, ſo that he would be aiding and aſſiſting to him with his Councell and advice, for the ſuppreſſing and paſſing of thoſe oppoſitions and perils, which were in the way yet unpaſsed; both agreed rejoyced, and on they journied, with all reciprocall officiouſneſs, and reſpect each to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (the weake man he wanted not ſupply or ſupport, the other he wanted no comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table words, councell, or politick advice) untill after many extremities and ſtraights paſt) they came to the laſt and greateſt; and that was a ſteepe craggie mountaine, full of ſtraight paſsages, ſlippery by-waies, and dubious windings, with deſperate precipices on each ſide, the faire and ſafe way which lede to a better end, lying direct in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle. Here theſe two Travellers were put to a ſtand, the weake wearied man was not able of himſelfe to aſsend, the other notwithſtanding his ſtrength, durſt not adventure alone, leſt he ſhould ſlip and fall, or looſe his way, and become a pray at length, the weake man lends the other his ſtaffe to ſtay him up, and defend him, and the ſtrong man by his ſtrength takes up the weake, and ſo they both with much hazzard and trouble gat up to the top of this incaceſsable Mountaine; and now they might ſee the long deſired end of their journy, and themſelves paſt all danger, which made them both glad, and to congratulate: <note n="*" place="margin">Obſerve.</note> But the weary weake man, having now beene brought as the charge and by the ſtrength and ſupport of the other, through all ſtraites and difficulties, and knowing himſelfe to be much in arreare to his friendly fellow Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and that he would expect ſatisfaction and recompence, and like benificence from him, when they were at reſt, and all things were accompliſhed: He tooke his ſtaffe from
<pb facs="tcp:164386:10"/> him, (which he had lent him for a ſtay and defence unto him untill he had carried him up the hill) and taking an occaſion to quarrell with him, about ſome ſlip, denyall of ſome monies, or neglect of his advice, fell upon him and beate him, bound him, and robbed him of his mony and treaſure, and ſo left him in the middeſt of a thicket, deſtitute and ſo deſtroyed and undone. The weake weary man, yee may ſuppoſe to be the Parliament: The ſtronger and better provided, to be the wiſe Lord Major, Aldermen, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>councel-men, with the reſt of the Preſbyteriall faction in London: The Mountaine to be the Preſbyters deſigne: and the Staffe to be the Militia, which is now put into the hands of the Preſbyterian party in London. The application I leave to the appeheeſion of them, and of all judicious Citizens, And Commoners of England. And will conclude with wiſe Solomon. There is no new thing under the Sunne: that which hath beene is now: And what is there that hath beene, which may not be againe? Pramoniti proemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niti, fore warned halfe Armed, and (proeviſa minus loedunt) things fore-ſeen doe leſs hurt. I wiſh you really well, yee grave Citizens of London, both for your owne and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands ſake: and God make you diſcerning and wiſe, that yee may not by the diſsembling epiſtles and ſpeeches of a deceitfull hypocriticall Nation, and the ſubtill ſophiſtry of an ambitious aſpiring party in both Houſes of Parliament, ſuch as Stapleton, Hollis, &amp;c. and of the proud, covetuous Clergy, be made the inſtruments (after you have ſerved their turnes) of your own ruine, and the Lands.</p>
            <p>I could here take occaſion (as there is good reaſon, howſoever what is for preſent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitted, is not forgot) to ſhew you (deare friends and fellow Commoners) how ye have beene abuſed and betrayed, by this very party and faction in both Houſes, their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents and inſtruments from the beginning, at Sherborne, Morthampton, Worceſter, Edgehill, Kingſton, Bramford, Mewarke, Exeter Reading Thame, (O Thame) the Devizes, Chalgrove field, (whete <note n="*" place="margin">S. Philip Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton was there alſo, &amp; beheld a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far ffo twas he that would not ſuffer the queenes Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Salisbury or Blandſord.</note> noble Hampden, it is conceived, and who knoweth but it may in time be proved, was delivered to death) Lincoln, Boſton, Crowland, Cornwall, Dening<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-Caſtle, (where Mancheſter acted Treaſon) Newarke againe, and Oxford: Durham, Cumberland, Weſtmerland, even in every place, and all along, untill the Lord raiſed up Sir Thomas Fairfax to be a Saviour to the People, and that he is ſo theſe wicked men are offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But me thinkes I already ſee this ſerpentine brood (like the old Serpent) caſting a flood out after-me to deſtroy me and their defiled conſciences being like the Sea troubled: they ſend forth mire and dirt; wrath, and revenge, reproches, curſes, beagles, and blood-hounds, Votes, Orders and Meſsengers, like the Popes execrations, with bell, book, and candle. Alas, bene la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet qui bene vivit. I wiſh theſe miſcreants (for their ſoules ſakes) had no more cauſe to be afraid then I the righteous is as bold as a Lyon, but the wicked flees when none pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues. the theefe thinks every buſh, and every bulk a Conſtable. and a gaulled horſe hath no patience, when his ſore is rubbed: this Sir Phillip Stapleton knowes, for he hath good skill in horſe-fleſh. But ſeeing theſe vile men will dare to ſinne openly, and to deale fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before the World, why ſhould we be afraid to reprove them openly, and to declare it to the World? They declare their ſins as Sodome, they hide them not. Iſai 3. 9. they have (as the Scripture ſpeaks) a brazen face, and a Whores forehead; and why ſhould we be ſilent, and connive at that which all Chriſtendome ſees. or turne our backs, and be pymps and panders to out own ruines? Why ſhould we be more afraid (whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes) to publiſh their robbery, oppreſsion, injuſtice, and Treaſon, then they are to act and execute it contrary to their Oaths and duties?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:164386:11"/>
            <p>Our Law condemnes no man for ſaying the Cole is blacke, or calling a Spade a Spade, although of late many have been * impriſoned and puniſhed for no more, nor other <note n="*" place="margin">Such works, ſuch waies, &amp; means.</note> Marke thing in effect: yet the looſer will ſpeake, and the oppreſsed will cry out: nor by the power of heaven ſhall my tongue be ſilent, or my Penne be flack, for the cauſe of God and this miſerable land; untill they do ſet themſelves in a way that is right, and execute juſtice and judgement.</p>
            <p>Is it not more then high time to ſpeake and ſtirre, when our juſt and lawfull Petitions are not only rejected, but infamouſly burned as feditious, our inveterate Enemies armed our perſons for preſenting our grievances, illegally impriſoned: when we are voted out of our Rights and Priviledges contrary to all Law, and cuſtome of Parliamente. All men may now ſee, and plainly underſtand, that it is altogether vaine, any longer to uſe Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning, for that due right and liberty is denyed and debarred. We muſt, I ſay we muſt, if we will recover our ſelves and our Priviledges, uſe action. Neceſſity hath no law, and extream danger, driveth to extream means.</p>
            <p>And now know for certain: ye Trayterous party, ye falſe deceiptfull men, whoſe hearts are ſet upon wickedneſse, and whoſe heads deviſe miſchiefe, and violence that it is not your <note n="*" place="margin">Without the King meere trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent worſe then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</note> breaking open of houſes, taking away mens goods by force, ſpoyling of Printing Preſses, and impriſoning of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, without prooſe or cauſe, and puniſhing poore ſoules, who carry Books to ſell, will or can hide your ſhame, the day of your judgement is comming: your wickedneſs is manifeſt as the Sunne, and your actions both publique and private are ſo abominable, that they ſtink in every reaſonable mans noſtrills: yee are become odious, and have made your ſelves a reproach and a hiſsing, and the very abjects diſdaine and ſcorne, yee, inſomuch that the name of a Parliament man, is as contemptible in the thoughts of moſt, as the name is generally of a Committee-man. And thus doe the good and vertuous of the Houſe, ſuffer in their repute and eſteeme, by your vitiouſneſse. yea, your beloved friends and favorites cannot juſtify you, nor open their mouths clearly for yee, and what will yee do? what can yee doe. when God ſhall ſtirre up the People to revenge? Remember Straford and Canterbury, Finch, and Windebanke: Yee have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the People, and falſifyed your truſt to them: yee have broken oathes, promiſes, and all manner of aſsurances with them, under a pretence of redeeming their liberties, and making them free, yee involved them in an unnaturall and bloody Warre againſt each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and now yee your ſelves exerciſe more abundant tyrannie, and keep them in moſt ſtrict and intollerable ſlavery, under the pretence of paying the Souldiers, yee have by your Committees, and inſtruments, oppreſsed and robbed the Countries; and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there is no Army paid, no reparations made, no debts ſatisfyed, and thouſands of Widowes and fatherleſs and maimed ſouldiers unprovided for: under pretence of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the people yee have deſtroyed them, and under the colour of eſtabliſhing Law and juſtice, yee have taken away both: and although yee rayſed Armes to redeem the King from his wicked councell, and have ſolemnly ſworne to maintaine his Crowne and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and declared Book Dec. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4. that what you did was for his honour and greatnes, and the weale of his Kingdomes. yet though he be redeemed, he is not reſtored, nor is his Crowne and dignity maintained: Nay yee your ſelves exerciſe the Kingly office; yee I ſay it again, yee your ſelves exerciſe the Kingly office: For yee make Lord Keepers, Judges and Barons, grant Pardons, and give Commiſſions of Oyer and Terminer: I have known a meane man dye as a traytor for doing leſs: nor are the Acts or Proceſs paſsed under the broad Seale of any vallue: In all which ye are but uſurpers (I ſhould not miſtake if I ſaid Traytors) I ſay
<pb facs="tcp:164386:11"/> uſurpers, and take too much upon you; for by Law there is no ſuch power or right belonging to you, or inveſted in yee: You keepe the King under reſtraint, and with-hold him from the execution of it, and do not ſatisfy the World wherefore ye do it: you are like the Dog in the manger, which will neither let the horſe eat the hay, nor eat it himſelfe: yee will neither admit the King to do juſtice, and redreſs our grievances, nor will yee your ſelves: yee have made no other uſe of the Kings power and name, then to deceive, oppreſs, and abuſe the People.</p>
            <p>Is this to do for his honour and greatnes, and the good of his Kingdomes: contrarium verò eſt verum, the contrary is true, by true.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake not in favour of his Majeſty further then conſcience and <note n="*" place="margin">Do unto all men as ye would be done unto.</note> equity, the Lord my maker knowes I am ſincerely for truth and juſtice, without partiallity, and againſt the contrary, whereſoever, or in whomſoever I find it: but a traytor or felon by the Law looſeth not any of his franchizes, poſseſſions or eſtate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be convict: let Ceſar have his due, and us the free Commons ours: if not, I do not doubt, but you will in due time have yours: If the King be King let him raign: if he have otherwiſe deſerved, why proceed you not legally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, that the World may ſee and judge, and yee be cleared of all callumny and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſion? But as you do, and deale with us, ſo yee deale with him: Us yee do unjuſtly impriſon and oppreſs, rob, and ſpoyle, deſtroy our Liberties, take away our eſtates, and undoe our Families, and ſhew us no Law, Cauſe or Reaſon, but a tyrannicall, unjuſt, ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, or treaſonable Vote, Order, or Ordinance: (Sic vultis, ſic jubetis, ſtat pro ratione voluntas:) Your Arbitrary wills are become Englands Lawes.</p>
            <p>And would yee know yee Commons of England, why the King is not in all this time brought home, nor any thing reſolved nor determined of him? I will tell you (deare friends) what I conceive I ſee: The Earle of Mancheſter, M Hollis, Stapleton, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who are abſolutely the chiefe inſtrumentall cauſes of all the evils, wee have lately ſuffered, and do ſtill ſuſtaine, and ſome of which have received vaſt ſummes of monies, whereof they know themſelves unable to give any good account, are in danger to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed as traytors: and deceivers, and be ſacrificed to juſtice: and therefore through their power, prevalency, and pollicy, a ſettlement betweene King and Parliament is deferred: becauſe by reaſon of the Army, whoſe integrity and zeale for juſtice they feare (and therefore only would diſband them) they cannot impoſe ſuch particular, peculiar condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon the King, as will fully ſecure them, and conduce to their Preſbyterian deſigne: this I doe beleeve, is the ſumme of all. But muſt the King and his People be ſtill divided, the breach lye open, and the difference uncompoſed, the Kingdome unſetled, the peoples peace and happineſs ſtill delayed, and our miſeries ſtill prolonged and continued, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the unjuſt deſires of a company of matchleſs Machiavllian traytors, who to ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, have endeavoured by all meanes to deſtroy us: Muſt wee languiſh in our ſufferings and ſorrwes, to waite their opportunities? It is neither meet nor right it ſhould be ſo, nor prudence or wiſedome to permit it ſo, let us therefore have an end of our troubles and diſtractions, or elſe apply our ſelves to put an end to their tyranny, treaſon, and Lordlineſs, that they may not wholly and utterly lay us waſt, and ruine us. And if in caſe of the Kings failing of his truſt, and denyall to ſettle the Militia or ſtrength of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in ſuch hands, and in ſuch a way, as the people may be thereby ſafe and ſecured, the Parliament (the repreſentative body) may for the ſafety of His Majeſty, and Kingdomes, take the diſpoſe and ordering of it into their hands: then by the ſame rule, forſomuch as the Parliament have failed of their truſt, and put the Militia and ſtrength of the Kingdome into ſuch hands, and in ſuch a way, as wee cannot confide or be ſafe in: Wee the free
<pb facs="tcp:164386:12"/> Commons of England, the reall and eſsentiall body polliticke, or any part of us, may or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and diſpoſe of our owne Armes and ſtrength, for our owne preſervation and ſafety; and the Army in particular (without queſtion) may lawfully retaine, order and diſpoſe of their armes and ſtrength, to and for the preſervation and ſafety of the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the principall end for which they were raiſed. This is the Parliaments owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as you may read in Booke Declarations page 93. and 150. and therefore I hope neither hereſie nor ſchiſme, blaſphemy nor treaſon. I have done, and a ruſh for him that is angry, and as much for him who is fearefull in a juſt cauſe: Let ſuch weigh well that ſaying of the holy Spirit, Prov. 29. 25. and then happily they may looke up and take courage: The feare of man bringeth a ſnare, but whoſoever truſteth in the Lord ſhall be ſafe. (Timida probitas, nunquam Reipublicae, eſt utilis.) Cowardly honeſty is never pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable, to the Common-wealth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
